<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jose Abells Reasearch Blog - Publications</title><link href="https://joseabell.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://joseabell.com/feeds/publications.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://joseabell.com/</id><updated>2020-06-30T23:33:09-07:00</updated><entry><title>Paper04 - Modelling the cyclic ratcheting of sands through memory-enhanced bounding surface plasticity.</title><link href="https://joseabell.com/posts/2020/paper04-modelling-the-cyclic-ratcheting-of-sands-through-memory-enhanced-bounding-surface-plasticity.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-30T23:33:09-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-30T23:33:09-07:00</updated><author><name>jaabell</name></author><id>tag:joseabell.com,2020-06-30:/posts/2020/paper04-modelling-the-cyclic-ratcheting-of-sands-through-memory-enhanced-bounding-surface-plasticity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote class="highlights"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modelling and simulation of cyclic sand ratcheting is …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote class="highlights"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modelling and simulation of cyclic sand ratcheting is tackled via a plasticity model formulated withinthe well-known critical state, bounding surface SANISAND framework. For this purpose, a third locus –termed ‘memory surface’ – is cast into the constitutive formulation, so as to phenomenologically capturemicro-mechanical, fabric-related processes directly relevant to the cyclic response. The predictive capabilityof the model under numerous loading cycles (‘high-cyclic’ loading) is explored with focus on drainedloading conditions, and validated against experimental test results from the literature – including triaxial,simple shear and oedometer cyclic loading. The model proves capable of reproducing the transition fromratcheting to shakedown response, in combination with a single set of soil parameters for different initial,boundary and loading conditions. This work contributes to the analysis of soil-structure interaction underhigh-cyclic loading events, such as those induced by environmental and/or traffic loads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!-- PELICAN_BEGIN_SUMMARY --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first paper fruit of the on-going collaboration with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://online-learning.tudelft.nl/instructors/federico-pisano/"&gt;Federico Pisanò&lt;/a&gt; at TU Delft. Here we tackle the problem of formulating a constitutive model, derived from the SAniSand framework by Yannis Dafalias, which can replicate the &lt;em&gt;ratcheting&lt;/em&gt; phenomenon on sands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is ratcheting?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- PELICAN_END_SUMMARY --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a ratchet! Ratchetin' is what it do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="I am the ratchet." src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/ksbd0a86m4728wk/ratchet-2.png?raw=1" style="width: 40%;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a ratchet. It ratchets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all seriousness, when soils are subjected to asymmetrical loading, for example because there may be a static shear load acting on it and then it gets shaken, the soil accumulates irrecoverable strain as it cycles. Typical constitutive models predict a constant rate of strain accumulation for this type of loading, and that is what needs to be fixed. Only &lt;em&gt;drained&lt;/em&gt; ratcheting response is pursued here, the &lt;em&gt;undrained&lt;/em&gt; behavior is get its own (already accepted) article (see &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Least_publishable_unit"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; for more info on this publishing strategy. &lt;em&gt;(joke Fede)&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, Federico and his great PhD student Haoyuan Liu together with Andrea Diambra at Bristol University integrated the idea of &lt;em&gt;memory surface&lt;/em&gt; (which was applied to granular soils by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://research-information.bris.ac.uk/en/publications/memory-surface-hardening-model-for-granular-soils-under-repeated-"&gt;Corti and Diambra in 2016&lt;/a&gt;) to extend the SAniSand constitutive and fix this. We affectionately baptized this model &lt;cite&gt;RatchySand&lt;/cite&gt;... a play on the SAniSand origins of the model and ratchyness. Officially we call the model &lt;cite&gt;SAniSand-MS&lt;/cite&gt;, in line with other models that have been developed in the same family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The team." src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/xis1190jcxkv410/ratchy_team.png?raw=1" style="width: 100%;" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of memory surface (MS) is a way to keep track of stress states that the soil has &lt;em&gt;visited&lt;/em&gt; previously, a type of soil fabric effect. When the soil re-visits this area then it should &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt; and respond with higher stiffness. Its explained in greater depth in the article, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/328211282_Modelling_the_cyclic_ratcheting_of_sands_through_memory-enhanced_bounding_surface_plasticity"&gt;go read it to get the best experience&lt;/a&gt;. The main point is that SAniSand's fabric tensor gets replaced with a new formulation based on the MS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The memory surface" src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/sqc6efifafocw2c/fig1-deviatoric.png?raw=1" style="width: 60%;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The memory surface remains within the yield surface which remains within the bounding surface throughout material response. The more surfaces the better.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model adds a few extra parameters to the original formulation, these parameters control the way the memory surface &lt;em&gt;hardens&lt;/em&gt; and expands or contracts, all while ensuring that the yield surface stays within the MS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Calibration" src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/rb6adj20w3qhl1c/fig3-calibration.png?raw=1" style="width: 100%;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Calibration of the new model parameters requires cyclic asymmetric DSS or Drained Triaxial data... for a lot of cycles... many. (Calibration data comes from&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/282252289_Explicit_Accumulation_Model_for_Non-cohesive_Soils_under_Cyclic_Loading"&gt;Wichtman et. al. 2005&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q-\epsilon_a\)&lt;/span&gt; plot the constitutive response is shown to reach a limiting value for increasing number of cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Response" src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/clz3s9odnbze3xg/fig2-response.png?raw=1" style="width: 100%;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Response&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be askin: &lt;em&gt;but what did&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;do José&lt;/em&gt;. My humble contribution was to implement this constitutive model for general states of stress in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://opensees.berkeley.edu/"&gt;OpenSees&lt;/a&gt;. For some time I've been in the developer team for OpenSees... which means my portrait appears on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/OpenSees"&gt;OpenSees Project github page&lt;/a&gt; (which is nice).  Anyway, the process of implementing and testing the model on OpenSees gave some nice insights into the model and allowed testing in some uncharted territory of the deviatoric plane. The idea, obviously, is to follow-up with some FEM applications using the power of this new tool. We already have some things to show for this, which are coming up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just would like to close thanking my collaborators: Federico, Andrea and most especially he who did the hard work Haoyuan. Y'all rock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type='text/javascript'&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "left",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js','color.js','mhchem.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'gray ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Publications"></category><category term="Papers"></category><category term="Constitutive Modeling"></category></entry><entry><title>Paper03 - Earthquake Soil Structure Interaction of Nuclear Power Plants, differences in response to 3-D, 3 × 1-D, and 1-D excitations</title><link href="https://joseabell.com/posts/2018/paper03-earthquake-soil-structure-interaction-of-nuclear-power-plants-differences-in-response-to-3-d-3-1-d-and-1-d-excitations.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-20T10:50:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-20T10:50:00-08:00</updated><author><name>jaabell</name></author><id>tag:joseabell.com,2018-02-20:/posts/2018/paper03-earthquake-soil-structure-interaction-of-nuclear-power-plants-differences-in-response-to-3-d-3-1-d-and-1-d-excitations.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summary: &lt;strong&gt;Finally!&lt;/strong&gt; First paper since PhD was accepted for publication …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summary: &lt;strong&gt;Finally!&lt;/strong&gt; First paper since PhD was accepted for publication. I'll take this opportunity to start a tradition and review my own papers here. I think its important that I do this for several reasons. First, there are discussions that come up during peer review that are important but don't make it into the paper. Misconceptions about the presented work can be clarified to a broader audience here. Also, I can say whatever I want, specially opinions and thoughts that come from intuition and might not make it through peer-review, I'll be as critical as possible about these too and hope that my readers can discuss with me. I can post videos...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally!&lt;/strong&gt; First paper since PhD was accepted for publication. I'll take this opportunity to start a tradition and review my own papers here. I think its important that I do this for several reasons. First, there are discussions that come up during peer review that are important but don't make it into the paper. Misconceptions about the presented work can be clarified to a broader audience here. Also, I can say whatever I want, specially opinions and thoughts that come from intuition and might not make it through peer-review, I'll be as critical as possible about these too and hope that my readers can discuss with me. I can post videos and other additional content here and make them available to everyone for free. And, finally, this post will have a Disqus thread &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets get to it! Here is the citation so far (I still don't have an issue assign, going through editorial process): &lt;strong&gt;Abell Mena J A&lt;/strong&gt;, Orbović N, McCallen D B, Jeremic B. &lt;em&gt;Earthquake soil-structure interaction of nuclear power plants, differences in response to 3-D, 3×1-D, and 1-D excitations.&lt;/em&gt; Earthquake Engng Struct Dyn. 2018;1–18. [https://doi.org/10.1002/eqe.3026].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is simple: to show that the 3-D character of seismic motions has an impact on the structural response of a nuclear power-plant by comparing the response to 3-D motions with the one produced by an equivalent 1-D (1 component: horizontal) or 3×1-D (3 components) motion. Here is the NPP model used in the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And its fixed-base eigenmodes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was required by the peer-reviewers to include these fixed-base modes in the article. These are interesting, but they're not too relevant to the SSI system. SSI significantly changes the participation of the modes. I've found it useful to stop thinking in terms of eigen modes for these kind of problems, it is better to think in terms of the requirements of wave-propagation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the paper, I use the domain reduction method (DRM) to couple a 3-D seismic simulation of the wave propagation from source to site with a local site and structure model. This &lt;em&gt;domain split&lt;/em&gt; allows the fully 3-D modeling of the motions into the structure, accurately. Also, importantly, it allows the separation of the seismic and NPP simulation, using separate dedicated programs for each task as opposed to one big complex simulation. This reduces the computational cost dramatically and allows more modeling freedom. From the &lt;em&gt;free-field&lt;/em&gt; response of the site (e.g. with no NPP on top) equivalent 1-D and 3×1-D motions were developed using 1-D site deconvolutions in Shake and input into the model for comparison. Here's a plot of what the differences look like for the top of the containment building. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width="30%" src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/zl0nuu76pfhbcr3/positions_top_of_containment.png?raw=1" alt="Top of containment" /&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/18y3foxfrxcw1mq/node_733_disp.png?raw=1" alt="Displacement response" /&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/aahcmkkr8zvzhf9/node_733_acce.png?raw=1" alt="Acceleration response" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-D or 3×1-D waves deliver energy in-phase to the foundation of the structure, resulting in enhanced response when compared to a full 3-D response.  In this particular case, it would be &lt;em&gt;conservative&lt;/em&gt; (looking at response accelerations and displacements) to use 1-D modeling of the seismic input. But, here is a point that couldn't be made in the article, &lt;strong&gt;this depends on the system&lt;/strong&gt; and I have &lt;a href="http://sokocalo.engr.ucdavis.edu/~jeremic/6D_vs_1D_ESSI_for_NPPs/"&gt;found cases&lt;/a&gt; where the results are opposite: it is &lt;strong&gt;nonconservative&lt;/strong&gt; to ignore 3-D ground motions effects. This point needs to be made more clearly (future work), for different seismic settings and structures. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also ran this model using a non-linear constitutive model for the soil. Check out what the energy dissipation looks like under the NPP (not part of the paper).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="videoWrapper" align="left"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
 src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Kjwi_pmLgdI" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was submitted for review Jan 6 2017, it took over a year to get acceptance! Three iterations of peer-review were done. Admittedly, I did take too much time to answer. Tough year was 2017. Although the reviewers were very picky, which led to article improvement--especially the introduction--, the main content of the article changed little. We have the same results and conclusions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where from here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It think DRM-based SSI analysis is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; methodology to produce the highest-possible fidelity modeling of SSI. But generating these DRM motions is costly, we need supercomputers for that. Highly-detailed modeling of seismic motions is currently underway, it would be rather cheap for the researchers doing these simulations to also generate DRM-compatible motions for future exploration, making these simulations even more relevant. There needs to be an agreed format for the distribution of DRM motions, and a repository of validated motions to be used for modeling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it worthwhile? That's a research question in of itself. Clearly we can build to withstand earthquakes, so its not a safety-critical issue to use advanced SSI modeling. Might be an economic one. Maybe some case-studies can be reinterpreted in the light of 3-D motions to suggest that they were to blame in unexpected performance of existing infrastructure. Some structures will be more sensitive to these effects than others, which? how much so? under what conditions? is it necessary to model them in this way? There is great value in high-fidelity SSI modeling, is there a way to bring this into practice? All questions I want to answer in the years to come. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Publications"></category><category term="Papers"></category><category term="DRM"></category><category term="ESSI"></category></entry></feed>