<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jose Abell's Research Blog</title><link href="http://www.joseabell.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.joseabell.com/feeds/tools.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.joseabell.com/</id><updated>2014-06-24T10:48:59-07:00</updated><entry><title>Site now powered by pelican!</title><link href="http://www.joseabell.com/site-moved-to-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-24T10:48:59-07:00</updated><author><name>jaabell</name></author><id>tag:www.joseabell.com,2014-06-24:site-moved-to-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I finally completed the transition from WordPress to &lt;a href="www.getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;. The moment was right. Pelican is more
appropriate for me as it is much simpler to manage (I host my own webpage), more flexible in terms
of what I can do with the blog, requires no php or database&amp;nbsp;knowledge. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican is a python powered static &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; generator. I set-up a heierarchy of folders where I store
my content. Web content is generated using the Markdown text syntax. Pelican uses these &lt;a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/"&gt;markdown&lt;/a&gt;
files and the folder structure to generate the website &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; has some advantages over a database with server-side logic based website. The most
important for me is speed and low memory usage, because I want to host my own&amp;nbsp;website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it makes it easier to share code as I can include code snippets directly in the markdown text
file and it gets highlighted using pygments (python&amp;nbsp;module).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="http://danielfrg.com/blog/2013/02/16/blogging-pelican-ipython-notebook/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; I can
also now (to do) use python notebooks to blog directly. This is a nice feature as I will be
blogging mainly about scientific computing, showing some example here and there and&amp;nbsp;such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I can version control the website using &lt;a href="http://git-scm.com/"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; and automate site
updating using a git-hook on the server (thank &lt;a href="http://www.textandhubris.com/automate-pelican-with-git.html"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;).
This means I can clone my git repo, make changes and push them and the server will automatically
generate the website and deploy&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love&amp;nbsp;pelican!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pelican"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="hacker"></category></entry></feed>